"What Is the Safest
Metabolism Booster?"
Given the 60% surge in the
adrenal hormone noradrenaline
within minutes of just drinking
two cups of plain water,
might one get the weight loss
benefits of noradrenaline-releasing drugs
like ephedra, without the risks?
You don’t know until
you put it to the test.
Published in the Journal
of the Endocrine Society,
the results were described
as “uniquely spectacular.”
Drinking two cups of water
increased the metabolic rate
of men and women by 30%.
The increase started within 10 minutes
and reached a maximum within an hour.
In the 90 minutes after drinking
a single tall glass of water,
the study subjects burned
about an extra 25 calories.
Do that four times a day throughout
the day and you could wipe out
100 extra calories—more than ephedra!
You’d trim off more calories
drinking water than taking
weight loss doses of the
banned substance, ephedrine—
the active component of
ephedra—three times a day.
And we’re just talking about plain,
cheap, safe, and legal tap water!
Using the 10 Calorie Rule I explained
previously, unless we somehow
compensated by eating more or
moving less, drinking that much water
could make us lose
10 pounds over time.
“In essence,” concluded
one research team,
“water drinking provides
negative calories.”
A similar effect was found in
overweight and obese children.
Drinking about two cups of
water led to a 25% increase
in metabolic rate within
24 minutes, lasting at least
66 minutes until
the experiment ended.
So, just getting the recommended
daily “adequate intake” of water—
about 7 cups a day for
children ages 4 through 8,
and for ages 9 through 13,
8 cups a day for girls
and 10 cups for boys—may offer
more than just hydration benefits.
Not all research teams were able
to replicate these findings, though.
Others only found about a 10
to 20% increase, a 5% increase,
or effectively none at all,
pouring cold water,
one might say, on
the whole concept.
What we care about,
though, is weight loss.
The proof is in the pudding.
Let’s test the waters, shall we?
Some researchers suggest,
“The increase in metabolic rate
with water drinking could
be systematically applied
in the prevention of weight gain….”
Talk about a safe, simple,
side-effect-free solution—
in fact free, in every sense.
Drug companies may spend
billions getting a new drug to market,
surely a little could be
spared to test something that,
at the very least, couldn’t hurt.
That’s the problem, though.
Water Is a “cost-free intervention.”
There are observational
studies suggesting those who drink,
for example, four or more
cups of water a day appear
to lose more weight, independent
of confounding factors
such as less soda or more exercise,
but you don’t really know...
until you put it to the test.
And finally, in 2013, “Effect
of ‘Water Induced Thermogenesis’
on Body Weight, Body Mass
Index and Body Composition
of Overweight Subjects.”
Fifty overweight
“girls” (actually women,
ages 18 through 23) were
asked to drink two cups of water
three times a day half an
hour before meals over
and above their regular
water intake, without otherwise
changing their diets
or physical activity.
And, they lost an average
of three pounds in eight weeks.
What happened to those
in the control group?
There was no control group, a fatal
flaw for any weight loss study
due to the “Hawthorne effect,”
where just knowing you’re
being watched and weighed may
subtly affect people’s behavior.
Of course, we’re just talking
about water; so, with no downsides
one might as well give it a
try, but I’d feel more confident
if there were some randomized,
controlled trials
to really put it to the test.
Thankfully, there are!
Oh, I hate it when the
title ruins the suspense.
Overweight and obese men and
women randomized to two cups
of water before each meal lost
nearly five pounds more body fat
in 12 weeks than those
in the control group.
Both groups were put on the
same calorie-restricted diet,
but the one with the added
water lost weight 44% faster.
A similar randomized controlled
trial found that about
1 in 4 in the water group lost
more than 5% of their body weight
compared to only 1 in
20 in the control group.
The average weight loss difference
was only about three pounds,
but those who claimed
to have actually complied
with the three-times-a-day instructions
lost about eight more pounds
compared to those only did
the extra water once a day or less.
This is comparable to commercial
weight loss programs
like Weight Watchers, and all they
did was drink some extra water.